<?xml version="1.0"?>
<changelog version="0.9.5">
  <comments>
    <para>
      Three big changes this time: the grappling hook code has been split
      from CTF, the code responsible for changing levels has been split from 
      BaseQ2, and the code responsible for generating the DOM documents describing
      a level has been generalized and made more flexible.
    </para>
    <para>
      The GrapplingHook code still resides in the q2java.ctf package, but 
      is not tied directly to the CTFPlayer class anymore.  A new gamelet
      named q2java.ctf.GrapplingHook can stick a grappling hook in the inventory
      of any instance or q2java.baseq2.Player - which means you can use the GH
      in plain DM, Paranoia, BountyHunters, and hopefully in any future Q2Java game.
    </para>
    <para>
      The basic level changing code, which watches the timelimit and fraglimit, initiates
      intermission, and chooses which map comes next has been placed in a new gamelet
      named q2java.baseq2.LevelChanger.  This gamelet can easily be extended to use some
      other method of choosing maps or deciding when to change.  However, if this gamelet or 
      something similar to it isn't loaded, the server will never change maps.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Game class now creates a barebones DOM document when a level first starts, and 
      fires off a GameStatusEvent.GAME_BUILD_DOCUMENT event to give interested objects
      (such as barryp.map.XMLMaps gamelets) a chance to place map info into the document.
      It then checks to see if the gamelets have supplied any entity info, and if they
      either haven't at all or have included the &lt;include-default-entities/&gt; tag, 
      the Game will cause the string passed up from the .bsp file by the Engine to
      be parsed so that default entity info is included in the document before
      firing GameStatusEvent.GAME_PRESPAWN.  This new scheme makes it easy for
      multiple sources to contribute to the initial level document.
    </para>
  </comments>
  
  <class name="q2java.baseq2.BaseQ2">
    <removed author="Barry">
      Everything related to changing levels - from watching the fraglimit
      and timelimit to deciding what the next map will be.  This has all 
      been split off into a new gamelet q2java.baseq2.LevelChanger.  If that 
      gamelet or one similar to it isn't loaded, the map will never change now.
    </removed>
  </class>
  
  <class name="q2java.baseq2.GenericWeapon">
    <addition author="Barry">
      getOwner() method - to complement setOwner()
    </addition>
  </class>
  
  <class name="q2java.baseq2.LevelChanger">
    <addition author="Barry">
      New gamelet responsible for deciding when to change levels, initiating 
      the intermission mode, and choosing the next map.  Can easily be extended 
      or replaced with other gamelets that choose maps in a different way.
    </addition>
  </class>
    
  <class name="q2java.baseq2.Player">
    <change author="Barry">
      Class now implements GameStatusListener so it can listen for notifications
      of when to begin intermission.
    </change>    
    <change author="Barry">
      The two variations of addWeapon() are now public (was needed to support
      the new GrapplingHook gamelet).
    </change>
    <addition author="Barry">
      getIntermissionSpot() for choosing where a player should be placed during intermission.
    </addition>
    <change author="CheezHankrn">
      playerThink() now avoids calling fWeapon.weaponThink() if fWeapon is null -
      in preparation for future code that might have players wielding no weapons 
      at some points.  More work needs to be done though, since there's no real
      easy way to put the player in a no-weapon state - the game currently assumes
      you at least have a handblaster.     
    </change>
    <change author="Barry">
      print() method updated to pay better attention to the destination field
      of a PrintEvent, and display messages on the new PRINT_TALK_PRIVATE channel
      slightly differently than plain PRINT_TALK messages.
    </change>
    <change author="Barry">
      spawn() now fires a PlayerStateEvent.STATE_SPAWNED event to let interested
      objects know the player has spawned (the GrapplingHook gamelet is interested
      in this so it can slip a grappling hook weapon into the player's inventory)
    </change>    
    <change author="Barry">
      startIntermission() now calls getIntermissionSpot() to find an intermission
      spot - rather than being passed that info as a parameter.  This means that 
      different players may now see different intermission spots (unlike stock Q2), 
      but that should just make life more interesting. 
    </change>   
    <change author="Barry">
      teleport() now fires a PlayerStateEvent.STATE_TELEPORTED event to let interested
      objects know the Player has made a -drastic- change in position. (The grappling
      hook is interested in this - since it needs to reset if a player teleports).
    </change>         
  </class>
  
  <class name="q2java.baseq2.event.PlayerStateEvent">
    <addition author="Barry">
      STATE_TELEPORTED constant for events signalling that the player
      has stepped through a teleporter.
    </addition>  
    <removed author="Barry">
      STATE_SUSPENDEDSTOP constant wasn't being used, and had the same
      value as STATE_INVALID.
    </removed>
  </class>

  <class name="q2java.baseq2.spawn.item_breather">
    <change author="Barry">
      stateChanged() altered to only reset on death or disconnection, didn't
      want to reset when the player goes through a teleporter
    </change>    
  </class>  
    
  <class name="q2java.baseq2.spawn.item_enviro">
    <change author="Barry">
      stateChanged() altered to only reset on death or disconnection, didn't
      want to reset when the player goes through a teleporter
    </change>    
  </class>  
    
  <class name="q2java.baseq2.spawn.item_health_mega">
    <change author="Barry">
      stateChanged() altered to only reset on death or disconnection, didn't
      want to reset when the player goes through a teleporter
    </change>    
  </class>  
    
  <class name="q2java.baseq2.spawn.item_invulnerability">
    <change author="Barry">
      stateChanged() altered to only reset on death or disconnection, didn't
      want to reset when the player goes through a teleporter
    </change>    
  </class>  
    
  <class name="q2java.baseq2.spawn.item_quad">
    <change author="Barry">
      stateChanged() altered to only reset on death or disconnection, didn't
      want to reset when the player goes through a teleporter
    </change>    
  </class>  
    
  <class name="q2java.baseq2.spawn.worldspawn">
    <removed author="Barry">
      worldspawn no longer does anything with the "nextmap" spawn parameter.
      Anything interested in that info (such as the new LevelChanger gamelet)
      can examine the level document to find it.      
    </removed>    
  </class>  
  
  <class name="q2java.core.DefaultLevelDocumentFactory">
    <removed author="Barry">
      Class removed, most code now moved to q2java.core.GameUtil
    </removed>    
  </class>
  
  <class name="q2java.core.Game">
    <removed author="Barry">
      Everything related to the obsolete LevelDocumentFactory interface including setLevelDocumentFactory()
      and getLevelDocumentFactory().
    </removed>    
    <fix author="Barry">
      bprint() was causing double messages to be displayed on the console. Now
      it -only- fires off a PrintEvent, so it'll be up to some other code, probably
      some type of gamelet, to relay the message down to the console.
    </fix>   
    <addition author="Barry">
      getCurrentMapName() for finding out the current map name (duh). This info
      -could- be gotten from the level document, but the level document could also
      be screwed with, so the Game class now keeps a copy of the info that can 
      be relied on.
    </addition>  
    <addition author="Barry">
      getOccupancySupport() to get access to the object the Game class uses
      to fire off OccupancyEvents.
    </addition>       
    <addition author="Barry">
      startIntermission() to fire off a new GameStatusEvent to let objects know
      that they should go into intermission mode.  The new LevelChanger gamelet
      calls this when it decides it's time to move on.
    </addition>       
    <change author="Barry">
      startLevel() reworked to allow multiple objects to contribute to building 
      the DOM document describing the level, by creating a mostly-empty level document
      and firing off a GameStatusEvent.GAME_BUILD_DOCUMENT event when the level is first
      starting.  startLevel() also fills in the document with the info passed up from
      the .bsp file by the Q2 engine if necessary.
    </change>  
  </class>

  <class name="q2java.core.Gamelet">
    <change author="Barry">
      grabPlayers() now fires off a OccupancyEvent.PLAYER_CLASSCHANGE to let
      interested objects know that player classes are changing.  (Was necessary for
      the grappling hook gamelet, so it could register itself with the new player 
      objects).
    </change>  
  </class>
  
  <class name="q2java.core.GameUtil">
    <addition author="Barry">
      buildLevelDocument() can either build a mostly-empty level document
      that can be filled in by various sources, of a full one if a map entString
      is passed.
    </addition>
    <addition author="Barry">
      parseAngle3f() and parsePoint3f() moved back here from the obsolete q2java.core.DefaultLevelDocumentFactory
    </addition>
    <addition author="Barry">
      parseEntString() can parse a map's entString and insert the data into
      an existing DOM document.  Used by buildLevelDocument() and Game.startLevel().
    </addition>    
  </class>
  
  <class name="q2java.core.LevelDocumentFactory">
    <removed author="Barry">
      This interface is no longer needed due to the new level document building system.
    </removed>
  </class>
    
  <class name="q2java.core.XMLTools">
    <addition author="Barry">
       copy() method can copy nodes from one document to another - handy
       for merging multiple map data sources together.
    </addition>
  </class>   
  
  <class name="q2java.core.event.GameStatusEvent">
    <addition author="Barry">
      GAME_INTERMISSION constant for events that signal when intermission 
      should begin
    </addition>  
    <addition author="Barry">
      GAME_BUILD_DOCUMENT constant for events that signal when objects
      should consider contributing info to the next level's document
    </addition>  
    <addition author="Barry">
      getMapEntities() and getSpawnpoint() to find out about what was specified
      by the engine during the GAME_BUILD_DOCUMENT event. 
    </addition>  
    <removed author="Barry">
      constructor taking (int, String) parameters wasn't being used.
    </removed>
  </class>
 
  <class name="q2java.core.event.PrintEvent">
    <addition author="Barry">
      PRINT_TALK_PRIVATE constant added as a channel for private messages
    </addition>    
    <change author="Barry">
      getEvent() and releaseEvent() made public.
    </change>    
  </class>
 
  <class name="q2java.ctf.CTFPlayer">
    <change author="Barry">
      clearSettings() no longer worries about giving the player a grappling hook.
      This means that in order to have a GH in CTF, you must load the GrapplingHook
      gamelet in addition to the CTF gamelet.
    </change>    
    <change author="Barry">
      playerThink() no longer is aware of the grappling hook - the hook
      itself is now smart enough to register as a PlayerMoveListener and do
      what it needs when a PlayerMoveEvent is fired from inside q2java.baseq2.Player.playerThink().
    </change>    
    <removed author="Barry">
      teleport() method that overrode q2java.baseq2.Player.teleport() no longer needed
      since the grappling hook is smart enough to listen for PlayerStateEvent.PLAYER_TELEPORTED
      and reset itself as necessary.
    </removed>
  </class>

  <class name="q2java.ctf.GrappleWeapon">
    <addition author="Barry">
      This class used to be named q2java.ctf.spawn.weapon_grapple, but since
      that's not an item that appears in maps, it seemed cleaner to move
      it outside the q2java.ctf.spawn package.
    </addition>    
    <addition author="Barry">
      Objects of this class register as PlayerMoveListeners when the
      weapon is active, and playerMoved() is called so the hook gets a chance
      to pull the player along.
    </addition>
    <addition author="Barry">
      Objects of this class register as PlayerStateListeners so they can 
      watch for the player teleporting and reset the weapon if that happens..
    </addition>
  </class>
  
  <class name="q2java.ctf.GrapplingHook">
    <addition author="Barry">
      New gamelet that should add the grappling hook to q2java.baseq2.Player
      or any subclass.
    </addition>    
  </class>

  <class name="q2java.ctf.spawn.weapon_grapple">
    <addition author="Barry">
      This class was renamed to q2java.ctf.GrappleWeapon since
      that's not an item that appears in maps, and seemed cleaner to move
      it outside the q2java.ctf.spawn package.
    </addition>    
  </class>
  
</changelog>